Guide to the Set Design Drawings for the Film Mourning Becomes Electra
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Set design drawings for the film Mourning Becomes Electra.
1942-1952
YCAL MSS 798
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.33
(34 broadside folders)
The collection includes 34 charcoal set design sketches by Albert M. Pyke of scenes from the film Mourning Becomes Electra, produced and directed by Dudley Nichols. The drawings, dating from circa 1947, are on mountings measuring 35 3/4" x 29 3/4" and smaller. Each drawing has a title label which reads: "Dudley Nichols Production of Eugene O'Neill's Mourning Becomes Electra [title of drawing] William E. Flannery, Art Director."
Pyke, Albert M., 1897-1978
O'Neill, Eugene, 1888-1953 ( Mourning becomes Electra)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Dudley Nichols, 1947.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Albert M. Pyke (1897-1978)
Albert M. Pyke was an American film and television set designer and art director.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes 34 charcoal set design sketches by Albert M. Pyke of scenes from the film Mourning Becomes Electra, produced and directed by Dudley Nichols. The drawings, dating from circa 1947, are on mountings measuring 35 3/4" x 29 3/4" and smaller. Each drawing has a title label which reads: "Dudley Nichols Production of Eugene O'Neill's Mourning Becomes Electra [title of drawing] William E. Flannery, Art Director.
Arrangement
The drawings are arranged in the order in which they were initially inventoried by the library.
Motion pictures -- Production and direction; Drawings (visual works) -- United States -- 20th Century; Flannery, William; Nichols, Dudley, 1895-1960; O'Neill, Eugene, 1888-1953 -- Adaptations; Pyke, Albert M., 1897-1978
- Exterior of Dr. Hammel's House -- New York, 1865 (Box 1 (Broadside))
- Title frame with image of the ship "Flying Trades" (Box 2 (Broadside))
- Exterior Wharf -- Boston harbor (Box 3 (Broadside))
- Interior of Ezra's bedroom (Box 4 (Broadside))
- Brant at mailbox (Box 5 (Broadside))
- Deck at skylight --"Flying Trades" -- Boston (Box 6 (Broadside))
- Exterior of wharf -- Boston Harbor (Box 7 (Broadside))
- Exterior deck at gangplank, "Flying Trades" -- Boston (Box 8 (Broadside))
- Orin and Lavinia at gangplank, "Flying Trades" -- Boston (Box 9 (Broadside))
- Interior of apothecary's shop (Box 10 (Broadside))
- Interior of Lavinia's room -- Brant's boarding house (Box 11 (Broadside))
- Stair hall -- Brant's boarding house (Box 12 (Broadside))
- Interior of Mannon stair hall (Box 13 (Broadside))
- Interior of Mannon sitting room (Box 14 (Broadside))
- Exterior of Mannon home (Box 15 (Broadside))
  Scope and Contents
  Photograph of design mounted on board with charcoal titles, etc. Note reads: "Matte shot for #314, 315, 316, 317."
- Exterior deck at gangplank, "Flying Trades," -- Boston (Box 16 (Broadside))
- Brant and poison formula (Box 17 (Broadside))
- Exterior of the "Flying Trades" (Box 18 (Broadside))
- Brant and drunken chantyman (Box 19 (Broadside))
- Exterior of apothecary's shop (Box 20 (Broadside))
- Interior of Mannon study (Box 21 (Broadside))
- Exterior poop deck, "Flying Trader" -- Boston (Box 22 (Broadside))
- Interior of Brant's cabin (Box 23 (Broadside))
- Alleyway of "Flying Trades" (Box 24 (Broadside))
- Gangplank, "Flying Trades" (Box 25 (Broadside))
- Insert - Mail container outside boarding house (Box 26 (Broadside))
- New England seaport, 1865 (Box 27 (Broadside))
- Exterior of Mannon home (Box 28 (Broadside))
- Long shot of "Flying Trades" -- Boston (Box 29 (Broadside))
- Exterior of railroad station (Box 30 (Broadside))
- Exterior of boarding house and New York street, 1865 (Box 31 (Broadside))
- New England seaport, 1865 -- Long shot of town--Mannon home on hill (Box 32 (Broadside))
- New York Street, 1865 -- Lavinia follows Christine [1] (Box 33 (Broadside))
- New York street, 1865 -- Lavinia follows Christine [2] (Box 34 (Broadside))